FBI Files on Highlander Folk School on Microfilm 5898 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
FBI Files on Highlander Folk School on Microfilm
1940-1972
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)
5898 mf
0.11 cubic feet
1 microfilm reel
Articles, reports, pamphlets, correspondence, news clippings, records, publications, microfilm.
5727810
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, May 06, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The Highlander Folk School (HFS) in Monteagle, Tennessee, was established in 1932 by Myles Horton, a native Tennessean, who wanted to "provide an educational center in the South for the training of rural and industrial leaders, and for the conservation and enrichment of the indigenous cultural values of the mountain." The school accepted workers whom their unions considered potential leaders, and the unions paid most of their way through the school. These workers were trained in such endeavors as collective bargaining, contract negotiation, and strike organization, as well as less weighty, but presumably no less important, skills like poster-making and song-singing. Rosa Parks was trained by Highlander prior to her historic role in the Montgomery Bus Boycott, other activists who participated in training include members of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), Septima Clark, Anne Braden, Martin Luther King, Jr., James Bevel, Hollis Watkins, Bernard Lafayette, Ralph Abernathy and John Lewis in the mid - and - late 1950s. The state of Tennessee closed the school in 1961 because of backlash against the school's involvement with the Civil Rights Movement.
Highlander reorganized and moved to Knoxville, Tennessee, where it reopened as the Highlander Research and Education Center.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5717: Highlander Folk School Publications
American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU); Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI); Highland Folk School (HFS); Highlander Research and Education Center (HREC); Sea Island Progressive Club Center; Tennessee House of Representatives; Bagelon, David L.; Belmont, A. H.; Buttrick, Jr., William T.; Clegg, Hugh M.; DeLoach, C. D.; Dombrowski, James; Ford, Peyton; Green, William; Griffin, Marvin; Hoover, J. Edgar; Horton, Myles; Jones, M. A.; Jones, Robert F.; Ladd, D. M.; Laughlin, L. L.; Levy, Herbert M.; Masonk, Lucy R.; McGrath, J. Howard; Murphy, W. A.; Nichols, L. B.; Roosevelt, Eleanor; Smith, R. W.; Sullivan, W. C.; Swift, W. A.; Tolson, Clyde
5727810
- Sections 1-11, 1936-1972. (Reel 1)
  - Section 1: 4/1936-7/1941. (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1940; 1 (Reel 1)
      Scope and Contents
      1/29/40 on speech by James Dombrowski, chairman of the Highlander Folk School (HFS), on the philosophy and program of the school, including a list of HFS Advisory Committee members
    - Newspaper clippings, 1940; 2 (Reel 1)
      spring 1940
    - Various letters, 1940; 3 (Reel 1)
      alleging Communist influence within the HFS
    - Memo, 1940; 4 (Reel 1)
      12/6/40 to Bureau Director J. Edgar Hoover regarding request from Congressman Robert F. Jones to review the HFS file
    - Letter, 1941; 5 (Reel 1)
      4/9/41 from the special agent-in-charge (SAC), Knoxville, to Hoover requesting the bureau to develop photographs of HFS documents
    - Memo, 1941; 6 (Reel 1)
      4/14/41 from SAC Knoxville regarding report on the HFS furnished to William Green, president of the American Federation of Labor
    - Report, 1941; 7 (Reel 1)
      5/13/41 on the enrollment of William T. Buttrick, Jr., at the University of Florida
    - Report, 1941; 8 (Reel 1)
      6/1/41 regarding past activities of HFS faculty members
    - HFS promotional literarture, 9 (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1941; 10 (Reel 1)
      6/4/41 on Edwin B. Schutlz
    - Memo, 1941; 11 (Reel 1)
      6/6/41 from R.C. Hendon to Clyde Tolson regarding the HFS
    - Reports, 1941; 12 (Reel 1)
      6/41 concerning background checks of HFS personnel
  - Section 2: 7/1941-1/1942. (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1941; 13 (Reel 1)
      7/29/41 concerning background checks
    - Report, 1941; 14 (Reel 1)
      7/17/41 including the HFS Charter of Incorporation
    - Report, 1941; 15 (Reel 1)
      9/29/41 concerning the Institute for Labor Studies
    - Letter, 1941; 16 (Reel 1)
      10/4/41 from W.A. Murphy (SAC Knoxville) to Hoover concerning Myles Horton
    - Letter, 1941; 17 (Reel 1)
      10/12/41 from Murphy to Hoover regarding status of the HFS investigation
    - Report, 1941; 18 (Reel 1)
      10/21/41 concerning HFS contributors
    - Report, 1941; 19 (Reel 1)
      11/29/41 on HFS personnel
    - Report, 1941; 20 (Reel 1)
      12/30/41 on all aspects of the HFS to date
  - Section 3: 1/1942-10/1942. (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1942; 21 (Reel 1)
      1/8/42 regarding Joseph Kelley Stockton
    - Letter, 1942; 22 (Reel 1)
      1/19/42 from Murphy to Hoover stating that HFS-produced publications, including The Highlander Fling, will be provided in future reports
    - Letter, 1942; 23 (Reel 1)
      1/28/42 from Murphy to Hoover regarding a synopsis of the HFS 1941 annual report
    - Letter, 1942; 24 (Reel 1)
      2/16/42 from Murphy to Hoover, including copies of The Highlander Fling
    - Report, 1942; 25 (Reel 1)
      2/26/42 on James Dombrowski
    - Letter, 1942; 26 (Reel 1)
      2/28/42 from Murphy to Hoover regarding a $100 donation to the HFS from Eleanor Roosevelt
    - Copy of the ninth annual report of the HFS, 1941; 27 (Reel 1)
    - Copy of Songs of Field and Factory, 1940; 28 (Reel 1)
      HFS publication, spring 1940
    - Letter, 1942; 29 (Reel 1)
      3/18/42 from Murphy to Hoover, including HFS promotional literature and additional copies of The Highlander Fling
    - Report, 1942; 30 (Reel 1)
      4/1/42 on interview of Horton concerning his activities in the school area
    - Report, 1942; 31 (Reel 1)
      6/17/42 concerning interview of a former HFS employee
    - Report, 1942; 32 (Reel 1)
      7/9/42 regarding the HFS benefit concert in Washington by Paul Robeson and other HFS activities
    - includes newspaper clippings and additional HFS publications, 33 (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1942; 34 (Reel 1)
      9/12/42 regarding founding of the HFS and other background information
    - Memo, 1942; 35 (Reel 1)
      10/23/42 from Hoover to SAC Knoxville ordering a halt to the active investigation of the HFS
    - Report, 1942; 36 (Reel 1)
      10/22/42 on summer session of the HFS
  - Section 4: 10/1942-6/1954. (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1942; 37 (Reel 1)
      10/27/42 from K.R. McIntire to Mr. Mumford, including HFS promotional materials
    - Report, 1942; 38 (Reel 1)
      12/3/42 on tenth anniversary activities at the HFS
    - Letter, 1942; 39 (Reel 1)
      12/14/42 regarding closing of file, including one HFS publication
    - Letter, 1947; 40 (Reel 1)
      2/14/47 from Assistant Attorney General David L. Bagelon to Hoover regrading the HFS
    - includes additional information, 41 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1948; 42 (Reel 1)
      3/18/48 from Hoover to SAC Knoxville regarding possible Communist "front" status of the HFS
    - Letter, 1950; 43 (Reel 1)
      12/10/50 from Myles Horton to Hugh H. Clegg, assistant director of the bureau
    - Memo, 1951; 44 (Reel 1)
      1/4/51 from D.M. Ladd to Hoover regarding response to Horton
    - Memo, 1951; 45 (Reel 1)
      1/22/51 from Mr. Belmont to Mr. Ladd regarding response to Horton
    - Letter, 1951; 46 (Reel 1)
      2/14/51 from the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) to Hoover inquiring into the investigation of the HFS
    - Letter, 1951; 47 (Reel 1)
      1/31/51 from Horton to US Attorney General J. Howard McGrath regarding bureau investigation of black students enrolled at the HFS
    - Memo, 1951; 48 (Reel 1)
      2/26/51 from Hoover to Peyton Ford, deputy attorney general, concerning correspondence with Myles Horton
    - Memo, 1951; 49 (Reel 1)
      2/21/51 from D.M. Ladd to the director regarding Baldwin's allegation of bureau activity at the HFS
    - Teletype, 1951; 50 (Reel 1)
      2/21/51 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding interviews of Myles Horton
    - Memo, 1951; 51 (Reel 1)
      3/5/51 from Peyton Ford to Hoover regarding correspondence with Myles Horton
    - Memo, 1951; 52 (Reel 1)
      3/12/51 from L.L. Laughlin to A.H. Belmont regarding an HFS letter alleging bureau investigation of interracial enrollment
    - Newspaper clippings concerning the HFS, 53 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1951; 54 (Reel 1)
      2/27/51 from D.M. Ladd to Hoover regarding complaints surrounding the HFS investigation
    - Letter, 1951; 55 (Reel 1)
      3/14/51 from Lucy R. Mason of the Congress of Industrial Organizations regarding bureau agents
    - Memo, 1951; 56 (Reel 1)
      2/23/51 from D.M. Ladd to Hoover regarding the investigation of the HFS
    - Letter, 1951; 57 (Reel 1)
      4/18/51 from Herbert M. Levy of the ACLU regarding correspondence from Hoover
    - Memo, 1953; 58 (Reel 1)
      8/25/53 from A.H. Belmont to D.M. Ladd regarding Jenner Committee request for information on Myles Horton
    - Memo, 1953; 59 (Reel 1)
      8/27/53 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding interview of Rev. W.A. Swift, Monteagle, TN
  - Section 5: 12/1955-2/1959. (Reel 1)
    - Report, 1956; 60 (Reel 1)
      4/27/56 regarding Myles Horton and his wife
    - Copy of the HFS 21st Annual Report (10/1/52-9/30/53), 61 (Reel 1)
    - Copy of "A Guide to Community Action for Public School Integration", 62 (Reel 1)
    - Copy of "Public Speaking", 63 (Reel 1)
    - Copy of Highlander Reports, July 1953, 64 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1956; 65 (Reel 1)
      9/20/56 from SAC Mobile to Hoover regarding the HFS
    - Memo, 1957; 66 (Reel 1)
      8/30/57 from L.B. Nichols to Clyde Tolson regarding increased activity at the HFS and the plan of events for its 25th anniversary
    - Memo, 1957; 67 (Reel 1)
      9/4/57 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding information that the HFS is becoming a center for teaching civil disobedience
    - Pamphlet issued by the Georgia Commission on Education, Governor Marvin Griffin, chairman, alleging Communist activities at the HFS, 68 (Reel 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 69 (Reel 1)
    - Letter, 1957; 70 (Reel 1)
      11/1/57 from Hoover to SAC Knoxville inquiring into civil disobedience activities at the HFS
    - Letter, 1957; 71 (Reel 1)
      11/21/57 from Septima Clark of the HFS soliciting funds
    - Copy of Highlander Reports, 25th Annual (10/1/56-9/30/57), 1956-1957; 72 (Reel 1)
    - Copy of "Official Statement of Policy" of the HFS, 73 (Reel 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 74 (Reel 1)
    - Pamphlet: "Communism and the NAACP," origin unknown, 75 (Reel 1)
    - Letter, 1959; 76 (Reel 1)
      1/59 from Myles Horton soliciting funds
    - Copy of 26th Annual Report (10/1/57-9/30/58), 77 (Reel 1)
    - Letter, 1959; 78 (Reel 1)
      2/2/59 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding action by Tennessee legislature to investigate "subversive" activities at the HFS
  - Section 6: 2/1959-6/1961. (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1959; 79 (Reel 1)
      2/24/59 from SAC Memphis to Hoover regarding support of Tennessee legislature by the Tennessee Federation for Constitutional Government
    - Letter, 1959; 80 (Reel 1)
      6/8/59 to C.D. DeLoach regarding John's Island Branch of the HFS
    - Newspaper clippings regarding police raid on the HFS, 81 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1959; 82 (Reel 1)
      9/11/59 from Hoover to SAC Knoxville regarding open protest letter from Myles Horton
    - Report, 1959; 83 (Reel 1)
      9/15/59 on the HFS
    - Newspaper clippings regarding trial, 84 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1960; 85 (Reel 1)
      2/29/60 from SAC Louisville to Hoover regarding the "Friends of Highlander"
    - Newspaper clippings regarding revocation of the HFS charter, 86 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1961; 87 (Reel 1)
      5/22/61 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover pertaining to latest legal actions and decision
    - Memo, 1961; 88 (Reel 1)
      6/29/61 from Hoover to legal attache, Bonn (Federal Republic of Germany), regarding furnishing information about the HFS outisde the bureau
  - Section 7: 10/1961-11/1967. (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1961; 89 (Reel 1)
      10/17/61 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding contingency plans for the HFS to move to Knoxville
    - Memo, 1961; 90 (Reel 1)
      10/25/61 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding prointegration activities at the HFS
    - Memo, 1963; 91 (Reel 1)
      6/20/63 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding information about racial matters
    - Memo, 1963; 92 (Reel 1)
      7/18/63 from R.W. Smith to W.C. Sullivan regarding requests from Senator Warren G. Magnuson and Congressman Jeffery Cohilan concerning racial agitation
    - Newspaper clippings, 93 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1963; 94 (Reel 1)
      7/26/63 from F.J. Baumgardner to W.C. Sullivan regarding Highlander Research and Education Center (HREC), Knoxville, and request for list of officers, teachers, and students
    - Memo, 1964; 95 (Reel 1)
      8/13/64 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding update on situation
    - Memo, 1964; 96 (Reel 1)
      7/7/64 from SAC Knoxville regarding the Washington Committee for the HFS
    - Memo, 1964; 97 (Reel 1)
      8/28/64 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding voter registration drive at the Sea Island Progressive Club Center, St. John's Island, SC
    - Memo, 1964; 98 (Reel 1)
      9/10/64 from SAC Savannah to Hoover regarding the HREC
    - Memo, 1964; 99 (Reel 1)
      7/27/64 from M.A. Jones to C.D. DeLoach regarding request by Congressman Roman C. Purinski for information about the HFS
    - Airtel, 1965; 100 (Reel 1)
      4/6/65 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover concerning information on student march on Washington, co-sponsored by the HREC
    - Newspaper clippings, 101 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1965; 102 (Reel 1)
      10/19/65 from SAC Louisville to Hoover regarding vandalism against the HREC
    - Letter, 1965; 103 (Reel 1)
      10/19/65 from Hoover to chief, US Secret Service, regarding the HREC
    - Memo, 1967; 104 (Reel 1)
      4/13/67 from SAC Louisville to Hoover regarding vote by the Tennessee House of Representatives to start a second legislative investigation of the HREC
    - Copy of Tennessee House Joint Resolution No. 14, 105 (Reel 1)
      authorizing a committee to investigate the activites of the HREC of Knoxville County and its affiliated organizations
    - Memo, 1967; 106 (Reel 1)
      6/9/67 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding the HREC
  - Section 8: 1/1968-8/1972. (Reel 1)
    - Miscellaneous letters to the bureau requesting information about the HFS and the HREC, 1968-1972; 107 (Reel 1)
  - Section 9: 11/1940-6/1967., 108 (Reel 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, arranged chronologically, 1940-1967 (Reel 1)
  - Section 10: 1/20/1958., 109 (Reel 1)
    - Memo, 1958; 110 (Reel 1)
      1/20/1958 from SAC Knoxville to director regarding attempt to blow up the HFS
  - Section 11: 3/1959-9/1963. (Reel 1)
    - Teletype, 1959; 111 (Reel 1)
      3/16/59 from SAC Memphis to Hoover regarding bomb threat received at the HFS
    - Airtel, 1963; 112 (Reel 1)
      9/6/63 from SAC Knoxville to Hoover regarding bomb threat received at the HREC